Today
is the 133, but we're a little behind so we start on
132b, top, very top of the page, השוחט לכהן ולעובד כוכבים פטור
מן המתנות, Hashochet L'Kohen Ul'Oved Kochavim Patur Min HaMatanot, two dots.
So the משנה Mishnah had spoken about the focus on the one
who is doing the שחט, shechting, that
and we had sort of framed that in the גמרא Gemara as
well by רבא, Rava, we're about to quote רבא Rava again, that
saying that your the sort of כהן's Kohen person that he deals
with is the שוחט, shochet, it's the שוחט shochet who has the
אפוטרופסות. apotropsut. But nevertheless the determination of חיוב chiyuv or פטור p'tur
of whether you're exempt or not is a function about for whom
the animals are being שחט shechted or presumably who owns the animals.
So if the כהן Kohen owns the animals or they're being שחט
shechted for him, it's a little vague whether the actual ownership is
the issue, right? One could imagine a case that it's your animal
but I'm buying it from you and you're שחט shechting it for
me and I'm going to buy the meat. The גמרא Gemara is
never really exactly clear about that distinction about ownership versus for whom.
Let's assume it's ownership anyway. If it's כהן, Kohen, then you're exempt
and if it's owned for by ישראל Yisrael or for ישראל, Yisrael,
then you're חייב chayav regardless of who the שוחט shochet is. Thank
you. But
the one who's obligated is the שוחט, shochet, but it's a function
of for whom it's being שחט. shechted.
The שוחט shochet could also be the butcher or the butcher, yeah.
זובח הזבח משלם
שה,
Zoveach
hazevach mishalem seh,
right.
So today really wouldn't be the שוחט shochet because שוחט shochet is
just sort of like someone who it would be the butcher.
No, but it would be too. I mean the גמרא Gemara certainly
had deals in בבא קמא Bava Kamma where basically it's my cow
and I pay a butcher a fee to do a שחיטה shechitah
on my cow. So the interesting thing is obviously if he doesn't
give the מתנות matanot to the כהן, Kohen, then the כהן Kohen
has to deal with me. But it sounds like the first level
of obligation is actually on the one doing the שחיטה, shechitah, not
the person who owns
the cow.
No, I'm saying it's the butcher.
Oh, no, not the butcher in the sense of the seller of
the meat. The one doing the actual שחיטה. shechitah. Okay? All right.
Yeah, Charlie?
Would the שוחט shochet then after the ברכה berakhah for שחיטה, shechitah,
then do a על מצות מתנות? al mitzvat matanot?
Oh, no, you don't give you don't make a ברכה. berakhah. It's
an interesting question. You don't even though there is a מצוה mitzvah
to give, you don't make a ברכה berakhah on the giving of
like תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u'ma'asrot, the מתנות. matanot. You make a ברכה
berakhah on being מפריש, mafrish, which raises interesting questions about why you
don't make it. In general, my tie-in to the more general fact
that you don't make ברכות berakhot on sort of interpersonal types of
things, like on צדקה tzedakah and so on, might have to do
with the fact that there's a sense that maybe there's a sort
of an ethical dimension is there is maybe the most prominent. So
therefore making a ברכה berakhah frames it as purely ritual, not as
not but it's not so clear because when you're giving to a
כהן Kohen it's different than let's say giving צדקה, tzedakah, in terms
of the significance of it. It's a good point, but you don't
make a ברכה berakhah on the giving, you make a ברכה berakhah
on being מפריש. mafrish. Do you make a ברכה berakhah on being
מפריש mafrish the מתנות? matanot? I don't think so. I should check
on that. You make a ברכה berakhah on being מפריש mafrish תרומה
ומעשר, terumah u'ma'aser, which changes the status. It gives the status to
the תרומה, terumah, changes the status of the grain from טבל tevel
to non-טבל tevel and so on. As far as I know there
isn't a ברכה berakhah for the מתנות. matanot. I will check.
But you can still eat the rest of the animal without it
being הופרש.
hufrash. Well, we're going to talk about that a little bit in
a little later, but basically the answer is yes.
What is מפריש? mafrish?
מפריש mafrish separate, separate or designate off. Okay, so let's go to
the text. השוחט לכהן ולעובד כוכבים פטור מן המתנות, Hashochet L'Kohen Ul'Oved
Kochavim Patur Min HaMatanot, so it says if you שחט shecht for
a כהן Kohen or a non-Jew you're exempt. וליתני כהן ועובד כוכבים
פטורין מן המתנות. V'lisni Kohen v'Oved Kochavim p'turin min hamatanot. Why not
just say a כהן Kohen and a non-Jew are exempt? Why do
you say if you שחט shecht for them? אמר רבא זאת אומרת
הדין עם הטבח, Amar Rava zos omeres hadini im hatabach, and that's
exactly what we're saying, that your you
the כהן Kohen or whatever, you go to the butcher. So it's
not so
yes, the ownership or for whom it's being done, being for a
כהן Kohen or non-Jew determines whether it's obligated or not, but the
emphasis is on the שוחט. shochet. If we would have said the
כהן Kohen is exempt, you would have thought that you deal with
the owner of the cow. But no, you deal with the שוחט,
shochet, but the ownership or for whom it's being done determines whether
you're obligated. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, so רבא Rava expounded, מאת העם,
me'eis ha'am, so this is the law from the people, ולא מאת
הכהנים, v'lo me'eis hakohanim, not from the כהנים. Kohanim. A כהן Kohen
does not have to give these gifts to another כהן. Kohen. And
that's the point. If it's done for כהנים Kohanim you're exempt. כשהוא
אומר
מאת זובחי הזבח, K'shehu omer me'izovchei hazevach, from those that slaughter the
slaughterings, הוי אומר אפילו טבח כהן havei omer afilu tabach Kohen במשמע.
b'mashma. So that's exactly this balance, that you don't care who the
שוחט shochet is, you care for whom it's being done. So that's
the irony, meaning that the determination of obligation or exemption is based
on who owns the cow or for whom the שחיטה shechitah is
being done, but the person with whom you deal is the שוחט.
shochet. So if it's a כהן Kohen who's a שוחט shochet for
ישראל's Yisrael cow, then he has to give you the gift. If
it's a ישראל Yisrael who's a שוחט shochet for a כהן's Kohen
cow, he does not have to give you the gift. Okay now,
אושפיזיכיה דרב טבלא כהן הוה. Ushpizichei d'Rav Tavla Kohen hava.
The guest, thank you, of רב טבלא, Rav Tavla, like the person
staying at his inn or whatever in his house, was a כהן.
Kohen. And he was, he you know, he he had a hard,
he was having a hard time financially. That's a phrase, דחיק ליה
מלתא, dachik lei milsa, which is, you know, which which means like
it's pressuring, meaning he he's having a difficult financial time. So אתא
לקמיה דרבי טבלא, ata l'kamei d'Rabbi Tavla, so his, so this guest
of his came to רבי טבלא. Rabbi Tavla. אמר ליה, amar lei,
and said to him, זיל אשתתף בהדי טבחי ישראל. zil ishtatef bahadi
tavchei Yisrael.
So he gave him this suggestion. He said, look, here's what you
can do. Why don't you go, and this was your question the
other day, David, why don't you go and get into a partnership
with the Jewish butchers? דמיגו דמיפטרי ממתנתא, d'migo d'miptari mimatnasa,
because you'll agree to be a partner with them in their
business, משתתפי בהדך, mishtatfi bahadach,
they will sort of agree to be a partner with you. Meaning,
so basically why don't you buy a, you know, why don't they
offer them, look, you give me a five percent interest in your
business for nothing, but what you get out of it, or whatever,
two percent interest, whatever's in their financial interest, what you get out
of it is that now you won't have to give the gifts
to a כהן. Kohen. Now it's actually a little funny why he
does that rather than saying why don't you go and ask them
to give you the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa lechayayim v'keiva. But maybe,
you know, but maybe I don't know, maybe that's less frequent, right?
If you get a regular, you know, how many times you שחט
shacht a cow that you get a זרוע לחיים וקיבה? zroa lechayayim
v'keiva? But if you get a regular two percent out of, you
know, it's more like of an ongoing stream of funds. Also, there's
maybe a whole list, long line of other כהנים Kohanim looking for
זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa lechayayim v'keiva. Nobody else had, who was it
advising them, but what? It was רב טבלא. Rav Tavla.
רב טבלא Rav Tavla
advising them to say, you know, you you want זרוע לחיים וקיבה,
zroa lechayayim v'keiva, get in line. But now go to them with
this business deal and they'll figure out about how they can actually
save money, you know.
So he, it didn't work, what we just said. What? No, ah,
so the question is what does it mean to be a partner?
So the partnership seems to be, and this is why the גמרא
Gemara is vague, seems to be that they're not just שחט shachting
other people's cows, they are actually, you know, they own the meat.
And then they, so they're like butchers like we would call butchers.
So therefore, since you've got a percentage of the meat and then
they sell it, but first they שחט shacht it, it's theirs when
they're שחט shachting it, and you're part of a partner in the
cows and in the meat, so therefore they are exempt, even if
afterwards they go ahead and sell. Okay, so your point is a
very good one. I mean, you know, every כהן Kohen is now
going to try to do this deal and all the כהנים Kohanim
are going to be out of זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim v'keiva,
which is true. And the גמרא Gemara does not seem to stop
and consider the larger, you know, you know, implications of this.
But I mean the point is the butchers are still making money,
so they're making money.
But the few כהנים Kohanim who are smart enough to realize this
deal and to go and speak to the butchers ahead of time.
Anyway, and then everybody else is locked out, right? Because a few
people already got in, got in on it. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, דמיגו דמיפטרי ממתנתא משתתפי בהדך. d'migo d'miptari mimatnasa mishtatfi
bahadach.
חייביה רב נחמן. Chayvei Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said,
sorry buddy, or he said to the butcher, whatever, you still gotta
pay. You still gotta give the gift, even though this guy did
this deal with you. Why? So אמר ליה, amar lei, והא רב
טבלא פטרן. v'ha Rav Tavla patran. So he said to him, but
didn't רב טבלא Rav Tavla exempt us from giving the gift now
that we have this כהן Kohen as our business partner?
So the, so אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him,
this butcher, זיל אפיק, zil afik, go give the gifts, take it
out from your possession, ואי לא מפקינא לך רב טבלא מאוניך. v'ei
lo mafkina lach Rav Tavla m'oneich. And if you don't take the
gifts, I am going to take out רב טבלא Rav Tavla out
of your ear. Okay, which was basically is like, you know, a
little dismissive or whatever, but it's basically saying don't give me your
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, you give your רב טבלא, Rav Tavla, you
give the gifts or I'm going to forcibly remove them and I'll,
you know, sort of I'll throw רב טבלא Rav Tavla out on
his ear. So why? אזל רב טבלא קמיה דרב נחמן. Azal Rav
Tavla kamei d'Rav Nachman. So רב טבלא Rav Tavla now heard about
this, obviously. He went to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. אמר ליה מאי
טעמא עביד מר הכי, Amar lei mai ta'ama avid mar hachi, why
did you do this? אמר ליה, Amar lei, I'll tell you why.
דכי אתא רב אחא בר חנינא מדרומא, D'chi ata Rav Acha bar
Chanina midroma, when רב אחא בר חנינא Rav Acha bar Chanina came
from the south, wherever that is, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, he said in the name of רבי יהושע
בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, זקני דרום, ziknei darom, here's again
the south, the elders of the south אמרו, amru, they said, כהן
טבח, Kohen tabach, if the כהן Kohen is a butcher, and again
presumably he owns the meat to begin with, so that would mean
that and then he's selling his own meat, which means that he
would be technically exempt, שתים ושלש שבתות פטור מן המתנות. shtayim v'shalosh
shabbatos patur min hamatnos. For two or three weeks we get him
off the hook. מכאן ואילך חייב במתנות. Mikan v'eilach chayav b'matnos.
After that, then he has to start giving. Technically you're right, he's
exempt, even if you are, here's what's implicit in the גמרא, Gemara,
even if you are, if as long as it's your meat, even
if you're planning on selling it, and here's where the idea for
whom you're slaughtering really seems to not be the issue, the issue
really seems to be who owns the meat. So if you own
the meat and are slaughtering your cows, even with the intention of
selling them to the general public, but nevertheless if you're a כהן
Kohen and you're slaughtering your cows, you're exempt from the מתנות, matnos,
even if you're planning a second later to turn around and sell
them to the general public. At the moment you slaughter it, it's
yours, you're exempt from the מתנות. matnos. Now, one minute, that's the
basic הלכה, halacha, but then he said, you know what, that's not
really good for the larger community, so we're only going to let
you off the hook for For about two or three weeks. Once
it's established that you're basically in the business, for the first two
or three weeks people could think like you're maybe שחט shechted it
for yourself and you had leftover and therefore and whatever and people
are still understanding that it's in context of oh you're a כהן,
kohen, you שחט shechted it, and therefore you're exempt. After you've been
doing this for two or three weeks, it's pretty clear that your
role is to be a butcher for the larger community and therefore
it is no longer proper or legitimate or whatever for you to
be off the hook. Okay, even though technically you are, right, as
תוספות Tosafot points out, there's no פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah
that gives you two or three weeks. So we have to assume
that this is all a rabbinic point. So technically you are, but
once you're established as doing it basically for the larger community and
you're not really doing it for yourself, then we're going to have
to make you pay. So that's why he said I don't like
this whole thing. Now of course it could also be your point
David, which is that it also subverts the whole institution of the
זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim ve-keiva let's leave this open. The way
תוספות Tosafot explained it, let me just check the תוספות Tosafot again.
Oh no, תוספות Tosafot actually does say that. Not that it's a
question about what people understand. תוספות Tosafot actually says exactly your point.
He says שלא ירגילו טבחי ישראל לשתף כהנים עמהם להיפטר מן המתנות.
shelo yargilu tibchei Yisrael leshatef kohanim imahem lehipater min hamatnot. Okay,
but then he says exactly that point. They did not want this
as a way of subverting the whole system. For two or three
weeks, it's not so clear that you've got a whole arrangement going
or whatever or you're doing it intentionally as this way, so we
let it go for two or three weeks.
And then there's a story that says
so-and-so butcher, so the story we're going to get to in a
minute. So let's take a look. So he said,
one minute, so then he said to him, אמר ליה, amar lei,
he said back to him, ולא עביד ליה מר מכי רבי אבא
בר חנינא? velo aved lei mar mi-ke-Rabbi Abba bar Chanina? Okay,
but why didn't you at least give me two or three weeks
like that, at least give this כהן kohen I advised the first
two or three weeks? אמר ליה, amar lei, הני מילי דלא קביעי
מטבחתא, hani mili de-lo kavia michtata, he said that Michael, that's when
you do not have a storefront. אבל היכא דקא חזינא קביעי מטבחתא,
aval heicha de-ka-hacha kavia michtata,
you have a storefront, it's clear you're in the business of selling
it to the community and therefore as if we let you get
out by having a כהן kohen as a partner or somebody be
out by having a כהן kohen as a partner,
everybody would do this, it would subvert it. So if it for
if a person is sort of a little private business, he doesn't
have a storefront and whatever and then either he's a כהן kohen
or he has a כהן kohen as a partner, so then we
could say, it's not like it's subverting, it's not so obvious that
you're doing whatever and it's maybe people think fundamentally you're doing it
for yourself and it was leftover, but once it's either regular or
once it's sort of a general institution and it's obvious and so
on and you got or you have your storefront, then we don't
allow it. So there you go David, exactly what your point is.
We have to be concerned about subverting the whole institution. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, האי כהנא
דלא מפריש מתנתא ליה הוי בשמתא לאלהי ישראל. hai kahana de-lo mafrish
matnata lei havei beshamta le-Elohei Yisrael.
So if you have a כהן kohen that does not separate off
the מתנות, matnot, which basically means one minute let me just sort
of see what hold on a second,
right, give it to another כהן, kohen, is under a ban in
the name of God. It's an interesting phrase, בשמתא לאלהי ישראל. beshamta
le-Elohei Yisrael.
Now, אמר רבא בר רב שילא, amar Rava bar Rav Shila, now
it's a little funny because you if you remember we learned yesterday
that what do you call it, that not yesterday, was it yesterday
or two days ago, that a כהן kohen does not have to
give the gifts to another כהן, kohen, right? So that's a little
bit of a strange, but what he's talking about here, unless what
he means is is that you are the butcher is a כהן
kohen but the בהמות behemot are not for a כהן. kohen. Okay,
so maybe there was an ambiguity there, the whole point is is
it a little strange, the butcher is obligated but it's a question
who owns the cows. So maybe his point was was that maybe
when the butchers were כהנים kohanim they weren't doing it and he
regardless of who owned the cows and he wanted to make that
clear and put an end to that. But the גמרא Gemara did
say earlier that if the butcher is a כהן kohen he doesn't
have to give if if it is a כהן's kohen cow we
don't force him to give to another כהן. kohen. Yes.
On the Artscroll footnote says the רי"ף Rif and the רא"ש Rosh
do say that it is when the כהן kohen is the butcher.
And not the owner of the cow. Correct. There you go. Okay.
So האי כהנא דלא מפריש מתנתא ליה הוי בשמתא לאלהי ישראל. hai
kahana de-lo mafrish matnata lei havei beshamta le-Elohei Yisrael. אמר רבא בר
רב שילא, amar Rava bar Rav Shila, הני טבחי דהוצא קיימי בשמתא
דרב חסדא, hani tibchei de-Hutza kaimei beshamta de-Rav Chisda,
these butchers of הוצא Hutza are under the ban of רב חסדא
Rav Chisda האי עשרין ותרתי שנין, hai esrin ve-tarti shanin, for they
have been under that ban for the last 22 years. Now you
read that statement you might be sort of saying he's just being
criticizing the butchers or pointing out that this ban is not so
effective, people are doing this anyway, but the גמרא Gemara thinks that
maybe there's a halachic significance to this statement.
What meaning we were saying that these are כהנים kohanim butchers.
כהנים kohanim butchers, it's not their meat but they're כהנים kohanim butchers
and therefore they're not giving it even though they should because again
it's a question about who owns the meat, not who the butcher
is. So the גמרא Gemara says למאי הלכתא, le-mai hilchata, for what's
the point of this הלכה? halacha? אילימא דשמטינן להו, ileima de-shamtinan lehu,
if the suggestion is hey it's been 22 years let's not continue
to ban them, it's not doing them any good anyway, והתניא ve-hatanya
we taught in a ברייתא, baraita, במה דברים אמורים, be-mai devarim amurim,
when do we say that you give somebody let's say lashes and
you're done with it? במצות לא תעשה, be-mitzvot lo ta'aseh, if somebody
transgresses a negative commandment. אבל מצות עשה, aval mitzvat aseh, if somebody
is refusing... Makin oso ad shetetze v'at shetetze nafsho. What? At shetetze
nafsho.
You beat him until until the point of death. Now it doesn't
literally mean that, but the point is that there is a difference
between what do you call it, there's a difference between punishment, which
is you know one set of lashes for a negative commandment and
really no punishment for transgressing a positive as opposed to compelling somebody
to perform. And that the basic statement is is that we will
not that you've transgressed something in the past, but we're going to
try to use whatever sort of strategies are available to us, pressures
are available to us to get compliance. Okay, so I don't know
if the Gemara how literally the Gemara says עד שתצא נפשו, ad
shetetze nafsho, but the point is it's not a punishment, it's trying
to force compliance and we will keep on applying pressure whether physical
or social or whatever until we get compliance. So even though these
butchers have not been doing it for 22 years, that's no reason
to stop. Now of course it might be proof that this tactic
is ineffective, but it's not a reason to stop. So the גמרא
Gemara says what?
Is this a הלכה halacha that you can forcibly make somebody pressure
in Israel today?
Yes, but in terms of if what you're asking is the question
about about כופין kofin for a גט, get, that's sort of what
I was thinking about.
No, I wasn't about a גט. get. I was going to ask
that. No, not just for גט get for anything.
In Israel today, the חרדים Charedim can feel...
Yeah,
I mean that is a good question. It does reflect right, right,
right,
right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right,
right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right,
right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right,
right, right, right, right, right, right, And this is not talking about...
All right, we're moving on.
We're moving on. Yes, it is very troubling for our type of
society and values today and so on. But I just, you know,
you should understand the framework. The גמרא's Gemara living in a pre-modern
time where the whole question about identity is very different.
They always had Jews who didn't do it, like אלישע בן אבויה.
Elisha
ben Abuyah. Right. Yeah, there are always people that don't keep the
laws of America, but you know, okay. All right, let's keep on
going. אלא אלא, Ella ella, so
why, what's the point of emphasizing these butchers have not have been
violating this for 22 years? אלא דכנסינן להו Ella de-kansinan lehu below
התראה, asraisa, we
we can find them now without any prior warning. They've been warned
for 22 years. If now we do want to shift tactics and
start fining them, we can do it without giving them any prior
warning. כי הא דרבא Ki ha de-Rava like רבא Rava קנסי אטמא,
kansi atma, רבא Rava sort of fined them a whole thigh of
an animal of of a butcher, a whole thigh if because he
refused to give the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim ve-keiva, he took
a bigger chunk of meat for the כהנים. Kohanim. Or רב נחמן
Rav Nachman maybe this was the next step, רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak קנסי גלימא, kansi glima, okay,
he took a cloak, which is a little bit strange, okay, but
maybe the point being it doesn't have to be from the meat
itself, you do what works. Okay, ואמר רב חסדא, Ve-amar Rav Chisda,
זרוע zroa now okay, so that's that's what we have. If כהנים
Kohanim are partners, you're exempt. If כהנים Kohanim are butchers but the
owners are not כהנים, Kohanim, you're חייב. chayav. And now we're going
to talk about don't we won't let you get away with just
having כהנים Kohanim as a as a regular partner in your business
as a way of getting out. That we're going to give you
two or three weeks at most and then we're going to close
that down, you know, prevent that. And now we're going to talk
about how much of a partner the כהן Kohen has to be.
Okay, so we are three lines down in the wide lines on
קל"ב עמוד ב'. Kuf Lamed Bet Amud Bet.
I'm sorry, two lines, yeah, three lines down. ואמר רב חסדא, Ve-amar
Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda said, זרוע לאחד וקיבה לאחד ולחיים
לשנים. Zroa le-echad ve-keiva le-echad u-lechayayim li-shnayim. Oh no,
first he's saying how you distribute it. You give the זרוע zroa
to one כהן, Kohen, the קיבה keiva to another כהן, Kohen, and
the לחיים lechayayim to the cheeks to two, which is a little
funny because you would think that there's not so much in the
cheeks, you think there's more in the זרוע. zroa. But it is
plural.
Well, it is plural, that's true. Anyway. Wait, do the cheeks mean
like jaws?
Artscroll translates it jaws.
Jaws? That's true. There's an upper and lower bone.
I mean it's the whole area, it's the whole mouth area. It
doesn't matter if you call it the cheeks or the jaws.
No, but this is actually part of it. This part actually comes
off, the lower jaw.
Well, it definitely comes with the tongue. Let's say, we'll see later
the exact the exact parameters of it. Let's take a look. איני,
Eini, is that really true? והא כי אתא רב יצחק בר יוסף
אמר בברייתא פלגינהו להו גרמא גרמא, Ve-ha ki ata Rav Yitzchak bar
Yosef amar be-varaita palginhu lehu garma garma, and didn't he say that
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they divided it bone bone, meaning they
chop it up into smaller pieces and therefore they don't give a
whole big piece to each person? So the גמרא Gemara says, התם
בדתורא, Hatam be-detura, that is by an ox. An ox is big,
so they break it up, each you know, they chop it up
into smaller size. But here we do the whole piece when it's
a sheep or a goat, we divide it up like the whole
unit.
You also want כהנים Kohanim to enjoy it.
If you want to, right.
When they say here to one or to two, mean up to
two, right?
No, it just means that would be the normal way of distributing.
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar
Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, אסור לאכול מבהמה שלא הורמו מתנותיה. Assur le-echol
mi-behema she-lo hurmu matnoteha.
So here we get to the concept of טבל. tevel. We know
by grain, by תרומה ומעשר, terumah u-ma'aser, if you haven't separated them
all off, then you and you eat it, it's actually it's a
biblical prohibition and if you haven't separated off the תרומה terumah and
it's the highest level of טבל, tevel, it's a very serious one,
it's a חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav mita bidei shamayim. That's טבל.
tevel. What about the animal that you haven't separated it off? So
there, there's no קדושה kedusha in the gifts, so presumably there's no
status of טבל. tevel. So he says, nevertheless, you are not allowed
to eat from it before you've separated off the gifts. So אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל האוכל מבהמה שלא הורמו מתנותיה, kol ha-ochel mi-behema
she-lo hurmu matnoteha, if you eat from an animal that the gifts
have not been separated off, כאילו אוכל טבלים. ke-ilu ochel tevalim. It's
like you ate טבל. tevel. So he is making the analogy at
least at a on a moral level, not on a הלכה halakhic
level. He's not claiming you actually violate a prohibition, but on a
moral level it's like you ate טבל. tevel. And the גמרא Gemara
says, ולית הלכתא כוותיה, ve-leit hilkhata kavateih, that it is not really
the ruling, there is not although obviously you have an obligation to
give the gifts, there is no status of טבל tevel before it
has been separated. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מתנות כהונה אינן
נאכלות אלא צלי, Matnot kehuna einan ne'akhalot ella tzali, when you give
the gift to a כהן, Kohen, he should eat it in a
way of showing like as we'll see in a minute, of showing
like of of כבוד kavod and you know, because all it is
you give it to him, there I mean we'll see in a
minute also about how they ask and how you give it. But
how do you look at how do you give things to a
כהן, Kohen, right? I mean sometimes the פסוקים pesukim combine כהן Kohen
and more often לוי Levi actually with the poor, like it says,
you know, ונתת ללוי לגר ליתום ולאלמנה ואכלו בשעריך, ve-natata la-Levi la-ger
la-yatom ve-la-almanah ve-akhlu bi-she'arekha, you give to the poor, to the לוי,
Levi, to the to the stranger, to the orphan because they don't
have a חלק ונחלה. chelek ve-nachalah. On the other hand, you know,
you're supposed to give them a gift because out of honor, they're
doing this important service, they're serving God, they're representing the people and
so on, you know, they're they're the religious representatives so you give
this... to them as a gift of honor. So here the גמרא
Gemara and maybe there's a difference if you look in the פסוקים
psukim where many times it talks about the gifts to the כהן
Kohen versus the gifts to the לוי Levi in that capacity. So
here the גמרא Gemara anyway says not in the act of giving
which we'll get to in a minute but in the act of
eating. They should eat it as a way of showing that they
represent this as like as some type of a gift that represented
their honor, their status, so they eat it in a way of
sort of of you know of wealth and of of of greatness.
So therefore this is the way the כהנים Kohanim should eat it.
They should eat it roasted ואין נאכלת אלא בחרדל ve'ein ne'echelet ela
bechardal and dipped in mustard. Okay, particularly we'll see that might have
been a way to eat the tongue because the tongue came with...
exactly, exactly.
So they have מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? אמר קרא amar kra
because the verse says למשחה. lemoshcha. This is what I have given
you for anointing which means לגדולה ligdula for greatness. כדרך שהמלכים אוכלים
kederech shehamelachim ochlim you eat the way kings eat. So you eat
in a way that shows it's very fancy and honored, you're an
honored person that you're eating this. So that also reflects on what
the whole nature of the giving of the gift means that it's
not just here's some meat but that it actually shows your status
and you should eat it in a way that reflects your status.
Yes.
Surprising because in זבחים Zevachim we learned that the כהן Kohen can
cook any of the food any of the קדשים kodshim however he
wants.
Yeah, that's an excellent point, you have an excellent memory. So תוספות
Tosafot says, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, ואין נאכלת אלא צלי
ובחרדל, ve'ein ne'echelet ela tzli uvechardal, ואם תאמר בפרק כל התדיר, ve'im
tomar beperek kol hatadir, you could have written this תוספות, Tosafot, אמרנו
בכולן רשאין הכהנים לשנות באכילה לאוכלן צלויין
שלוקין ומבושלין, amarnu bechulan resha'in hakohanim leshanot ba'achila lochlan tzloyim shlukin umevushalin,
cook it any way they want, cooked, roasted, whatever. ויש לומר דכיון
דלמשחה לגדולה כדרך שהמלכים אוכלים, veyesh lomar dekeivan delemoshcha ligdula kederech shehamelachim
ochlim, ונראה דודאי כמו שטוב לו ונהנה יותר מצי אכיל לו. venireh
devadai kemo shetov lo venehene yoter matzi achil lo.
You can eat it the way that you like best, however you
like your food best prepared. אבל אם אדם שטוב לו צלי כשלוק
ומבושל, aval im adam shetov lo tzli keshalluk umevushal,
but if you don't care exactly how it's prepared, they're all equivalent,
then יאכל צלי שהוא גדולה יותר. yochal tzli shehu gedula yoter. You
should eat the way that socially is recognized as the fancier way
of eating. So certainly you're entitled to eat it in the way
that is fitting of your tastes, but all other things being equal,
eat it in a way that reflects to the larger society that
this is a fancy way of eating your stuff. Okay. So, so
that is excellent point. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on. ואמר
רב חסדא עשרים וארבע מתנות כהונה, ve'amar Rav Chisda esrim ve'arba matnot
kehuna, the 24 gifts of the כהונה, kehuna, which we're about to
talk about, כל כהן שאינו בקי בהן אין נותנין לו מתנה. kol
kohen she'eino baki bahen ein notnin lo matana.
If you don't know them expertly, we don't give you a gift.
Now what does know them expertly mean? You might think it means
you got to test on all the הלכות, halachot, but רש"י, Rashi,
you
know which ones they are?
רש"י Rashi interprets it in the context of what we just said.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, שאינו בקי
בהן, she'eino baki bahen,
third wide line near the end, היך דין מתנה היך נאכלים בגדולה.
heich din matana heich ne'echalim bigdula.
You don't understand how to eat it. So it's exactly the previous
point. If you're not going to eat it in a way that
reflects the context in which this should be given and received, then
we're not going to give it to you. That makes a lot
of sense, right? Because we're trying to, we're trying to like preserve,
to cultivate a certain type of a social context for what it
means to give and receive these gifts. Because you could obviously understand
the alternative, like oh here's some meat, you know, or like you're
a poor person might be the context. We want it to be
a context of honor and respect. So part of that is your
understanding, I have to know how to give it, you have to
know how to receive it.
Applies to the כהנות Kohanot also?
Presumably, that's a good point, but yes, presumably the female כהנות Kohanot
as well with the ones that they are given. So, so the
גמרא Gemara says, but
although that was a lovely statement in the context of what we
just said, the גמרא Gemara rejects it. ולאו מילתא היא, velav milta
hi, that's not really the ruling. דתניא detanya we taught in a
ברייתא, baraita, רבי שמעון אומר כל כהן שאינו מודה בעבודה אין לו
חלק בכהונה. Rabbi Shimon omer kol kohen she'eino modeh ba'avoda ein lo
chelek bakehuna. If you don't agree, if you don't accept the עבודה,
avoda, you don't accept the way in which you do the service,
meaning you say I don't believe in that, I don't believe it's
from God, or I'm not accepting that's not my responsibility, I would
never do that עבודה. avoda. You don't accept the responsibility of the
עבודה, avoda, then you don't have a portion in, then you don't
have a portion. שנאמר, shenemar, as the verse says, המקריב את דם
השלמים ואת החלב מבני אהרן לו תהיה שוק הימין למנה. hamakriv et
dam hashelamim ve'et hachelev mivnei Aharon lo tihyeh shok hayamin lemana. The
one who offers the blood and the fat,
he is the one that gets the thigh, the right side for
his portion.
אין לי אלא זה בלבד, ein li ela zeh bilvad,
I only know that it has to do with this עבודה. avoda.
מנין לרבות חמש עשרה עבודות, minayin lerabot chamesh esreh avodot,
how do you know the other 15 עבודות avodot which are כגון?
kegon?
Here's a nice little summary list. היציקות והבלילות, hayetzikot vehabelilot, the mixing
and the pouring of oil on the מנחות, menachot, הפתיתות, haptitot, the
breaking of the מנחות menachot into pieces, והמליחות, vehamelichot, the putting of
the salt on the קרבנות, korbanot, תנופות והגשות, tnufot vehagashot, the waving
of and
the touching of it to the corner of the altar, הקמיצות, hakmitzot,
the taking of the handbreadth, הקטורת, haketoret, the burning of the incense
or the burning of the handbreadth on the altar, המליקות, hamelikot, doing
מליקה melika for a bird, top of...
that's why it's in parentheses, ומיצוי הדם, umitzuy hadam,
the squeezing of the blood for a bird. Okay, קכ"ח Kuf-Kaf-Chet of
קל"ג ע"א, Kuf-Lamed-Gimel Amud Aleph, הקבלות, hakabalot,
catching the blood of a בהמה. behema. הזאות haza'ot the throwing of
the blood, והשקאת סוטה. vehashka'at sotah. Now we're moving away from קרבנות,
korbanot, the ritual of having the סוטה sotah drink when the woman
suspected of adultery, ועריפת עגלה, ve'arifat eglah, the breaking of the neck.
Now we're going outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, which is still
part of what the כהנים kohanim do, the breaking of the neck
of the calf when you don't know who the murderer is, עגלה
ערופה, eglah arufah, וטהרת מצורע, vetaharat metzora,
the purification of the מצורע, metzora, also outside the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, right? The כהן kohen goes outside the camp to the מצורע,
metzora, ונשיאת כפיים, unesiat kapayim, and the lifting up of the hands,
בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ, bein mibifnim bein mibachutz, whether in the בית
הכנסת, Beit HaKnesset, in the שול, shul, in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash
or in the בית הכנסת. Beit HaKnesset. So notice we're moving from
like inside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to outside, and this one
is sort of in both. Anyway, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, how do
you know that a כהן kohen who does not accept
his obligation to do all of these and the responsibility of these
does not get a portion? תלמוד לומר מבני אהרן. talmud lomar mibnei
Aharon. It says the כהן kohen who throws the blood of the
children of אהרן, Aharon, עבודה המסורה לבני אהרן, avodah hamesurah livnei Aharon,
any part of the service that is part of the responsibility of
the בני אהרן, bnei Aharon, כל כהן שאינו מודה בה, kol kohen
she'eino modeh bah,
any כהן kohen that does not accept the entirety, אין לו חלק
בכהונה, ein lo chelek bakehunah, does not have a portion of the
כהונה, kehunah, which means does not get a portion of any of
the gifts. So that is our basic teaching, that you have to
accept the responsibility. טעמא דאינו מודה בה, ta'ama de'eino modeh bah, the
point is because you don't actually accept it. המודה בה, hamodeh bah,
if you accept it, אף על גב דאינו בקי בהן, af al
gav de'eino baki bahen, even if you're not an expert in them,
you still are entitled. Now it's interesting because there are different things,
meaning one is the עבודות, avodot, right? In that whole list, wasn't
תרומה terumah mentioned? Because תרומה terumah isn't relevant to the עבודות. avodot.
So that's sort of talking about things in which the כהן kohen
performs a ritual, right? And he has to be accepting all of
those, all his responsibility to do those rituals. Right? You could have
sort of said, you know, this is very different. The whole giving
of the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vekeivah is not related to
any ritual and so on. And there you have to, it's another
point, meaning, you know, it's that you know how to eat them.
But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara says that that were true, presumably it
should have been true by those rituals as well. Let's say I
accept doing the קרבנות, korbanot, but I'm not going to eat the
meat in a proper way. So it's never said that I can't
get the meat under those circumstances. So that was a quite lovely
idea because here we are talking about the idea that it's again,
this thing as a sort of social institution is not just the
obligation to give, but the context and the way in which it's
given and the way in which it's received. We don't go so
far to say that if you don't know how, you can't receive
it. You had a question, Charlie? Okay, Michael, yeah.
Similar to my question, but you said you were going to get
up to why we don't do them anymore. But then it talks
about נשיאת כפיים, nesiat kapayim, you know, inside or outside the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So how come at least מנהג אשכנז minhag Ashkenaz
doesn't have to do נשיאת כפיים nesiat kapayim except, you know, very
infrequently?
That's a different question. This is basically saying that you're not accepting
the responsibility. I understand. I'm not, when we learn, now I'm trying
to remember where נשיאת כפיים nesiat kapayim is.
Anyway, when we learn that מסכת, masechet, we'll talk about נשיאת כפיים.
nesiat kapayim. Where is נשיאת כפיים? nesiat kapayim? It is in, oh,
why am I blanking on it? רמב"ם הלכות ברכות. Rambam Hilchot Berachot.
I'm not where in רמב"ם, Rambam, where's in גמרא? Gemara? Okay, anyway,
let's keep on going.
Okay. משנה סוטה? Mishnah Sotah? יומא? Yoma?
No,
it's not יומא. Yoma.
משנה סוטה ל"ז עמוד ב'. Mishnah Sotah lamed zayin amud bet.
Yeah, there is a part of it in סוטה. Sotah. Okay, anyway,
I don't know. Okay, moving on. All right. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rabbah
bar Rav Huna amar Rav, so about eight lines down, חוטין שבלהי,
chutin shebalchi,
the veins in the jaw, I guess I was saying the cheeks,
the jaw are forbidden because there's blood in them, so you have
to, you know, remove them. וכל כהן שאינו יודע ליטלן אין נותנין
לו מתנה, vechol kohen she'eino yode'a litlan ein notnin lo matanah, and
if the כהן kohen doesn't know about removing them, so now it's
a כשרות kashrut issue, you don't want to be מכשיל machshil him
in eating blood. So if you know that he's not, he doesn't
know how to remove those veins or arteries or whatever, then you
cannot give him.
But whose responsibility to remove it?
Like it was barbers, they used to get a נשר? nesher? Right.
That was only things that right, were not considered people that people
normally couldn't do, and even there there was a פסק psak if
you could trust the butcher to do it. Okay, anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says וכל כהן שאינו יודע ליטלן אין נותנין לו מתנה,
vechol kohen she'eino yode'a litlan ein notnin lo matanah, ולא היא, velo
hi, that's not the rule. Why? Because you don't have to remove
them. אי בטויא, i betavya, if you want to roast it, מידב
דייב, midav dayev, it'll drip away. Right? That's what we say anyway,
that roasting always is a way of not requiring כשרות kashrut of
the blood because all, because the roasting, if it's over an open
pit, right, you know, then the blood will just drip away.
It'll simply מידב דייב, midav dayev, it'll flow.
Yeah, it'll flow. Where were we? ואי בקדירה, ve'i bekedirah,
and if you're doing it for a pot, so you have to,
you do have to get the blood out before you cook it
because it's all contained within the pot. אי דמחתך להו ומלח להו,
i demachtach lehu umalach lehu, so if you cut it and then
salted, מידב דייב, midav dayev, it'll flow away. So you don't have
to be able to remove it, which is a real expert skill.
You just know how to do מליחה. melichah. So you could say,
why should you say don't give him any meat? They won't do
מליחה? melichah? Everybody knows how to כשר. kasher. It's not a problem.
Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so said רבא, Rava, בדיק לן רב
יוסף, bedik lan Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef tested us.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef was his רבי, Rebbi, and he sort of
gave the students a little bit of a test to see if
they were paying attention or whatever. האי כהנא דחטיף מתנתא, hai kahana
dechatif matnata,
now we're getting back to this theme about the right way to
receive the gift. Okay, so a כהן kohen that grabs the מתנה,
matanah, so you know, he sees that there's a
butcher just שחט, shachat, he
runs
in... but to treasure the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*. Why do you run
in and grab? Because you wanted to do the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*,
it's such an important מצוה *mitzvah*. או זוזי קא מזלזל במצוה *O
zuzai ka-mezalzel be-mitzvah*, or maybe he is denigrating the מצוה *mitzvah*, right?
That he's, you
know, maybe
it's, it shows that he's ravenous or that he's not waiting to
receive, maybe, and besides whether it's a question of ravenous or not,
you know, it's the context in which you give something. You give
somebody a gift and they're sort of stationary and they're receiving it,
there's a very nice way of showing respect that way. To grab
it, you know, it's sort of, it's not a whole respectful process.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to touch on that. So
פשטינן ליה *pashitinan lei*, and we concluded the issue for him, meaning
we determined it by the following פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, because it says
ונתת *ve-natan*, you should give to the כהן Kohen. *Kohen*, ולא שיטול
מעצמו *ve-lo she-yitol me-atzmo*, he shouldn't take it for himself. So it's
a question, were they just answering as a technical halakhic point, or
they also answering in terms of sort of what it demonstrates and
reflects? That as they say halakhically you're supposed to give, there's an
act of giving, they also say and that really points to the
fact that to take it is not respectful. Besides that it's not
following the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, it's not respectful. So אמר אביי Abaye
*Amar Abaye*, מרישא הוה חטיפנא מתנתא *me-reisha hava chatifna matnasa*. אביי *Abaye*
was a כהן Kohen. *Kohen*, and he said I used to grab
the מתנות matanot, *matanos*. אמינא חבובי קא מחבבנא מצוה *Amina chivuvei ka-mechaveivna
mitzvah*, I'm showing my love of a מצוה *mitzvah*, I'm running to
do a מצוה *mitzvah*, right? So כיון דשמעינן לה *keivan de-shaminan le-ha*,
ונתת ולא שיטול מעצמו *ve-natan ve-lo she-yitol me-atzmo*, once I heard this
דרשה *drasha* and you shall give, which specifically means the כהן Kohen.
*Kohen* should not take for himself, מכתף לא lo, חטיפנא *michtaf lo
chatifna*, I stopped grabbing it. מימר אמרי *Meimar amri*, הבו לי *havu
li*, but I did go up to the butcher and I said
please give it to me, because I'm not grabbing and you know,
I'm letting him give it, and maybe it's still I'm showing my
desire to participate in this מצוה *mitzvah*. וכיון דשמעינן לה דתניא detanya,
*Ve-keivan de-shaminan le-ha de-tanya*, ויטו אחרי הבצע *vayet'u acharei habatza*,
this is about the sons of שמואל *Shmuel*, that they went after
the either money or bribery. רבי מאיר אומר *Rabbi Meir omer*, what
does this mean? בני שמואל חלקם שאלו בפיהם *Bnei Shmuel chelkom sha'alu
be-fihem*, they asked for their portion in their verbally. Now שמואל *Shmuel*
actually, you know, in the beginning of שמואל *Shmuel* it says איש
אחד מן הרמתים צופים *ish echad min ha-ramatayim tzofim*, you know, מהר
אפרים *me-har ephraim*, so and I'm so he was from אפרים *Ephraim*,
but in דברי הימים *Divrei HaYamim* it lists שמואל *Shmuel* and his
father and grandfather, great-grandfather amongst the לויים *Levi'im*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is assuming so it might be, you know, לויים *Levi'im* were
scattered throughout all of ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*, they were twenty-four, you know,
whatever, there were the ערי לוויה *arei Levi'im*.
So anyways, so שמואל *Shmuel* is assumed to be a לוי Levi
*Levi*, and it says so what was his sons doing wrong is
that they demanded their מתנות matanot לוויה *matnos Levi'ah*, their מעשר ma'aser
*ma'aser*, they said give me my מעשר ma'aser, *ma'aser*. Okay, so that's
they went after money, okay, they went after bribery or after money,
so that shows that even asking for it does not reflect well.
It's not interpreted as a desiring to participate in a מצוה *mitzvah*,
it's interpreted as desiring to get the, you know, to just have
the money, to just have the, to you know, to be following
the desire for the wealth, or whatever wealth is the wrong word,
but anyway,
the avarice I should say. So מימר נמי לא אמינא *meimar nami
lo amina*, so therefore since I see that it's not right to
ask for it, it doesn't look right regardless presumably of motivation, it
looks like avarice or something, so therefore I don't even ask. But
אי יהבו לי *i yahavu li*, but if some a butcher would
come by and give me it, שקלינא *shaklina*, of course I would
take. But כיון דשמעינן לה דתניא *keivan de-shaminan le-ha de-tanya*, I heard
in a ברייתא braita *braisa* that it talks about after the there
were there you know after at a certain time in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* the לחם הפנים *lechem ha-panim*, the bread,
you know, that they would distribute, it would there would be very
little and not enough to go around, I mean there used to
be a blessing and every כהן Kohen *Kohen* would get some and
would be blessed by having a part of the bread, but then
after even
a little bit,
right, and even a little bit, but towards the anyway the end
of the period there was a sense that there was very little
to go around. So what does it say? הצנועים מושכין ידיהם *Ha-tznu'im
moshchin yedeihem*, the more private ones or the more modest ones would
step back.
והגרגרנים *Ve-ha-gargaranim* חולקין *chokin*, they would be the ones that would grab
their piece of bread. So therefore משקל נמי לא שקלינא *mishkal nami
lo shaklina*, I also don't I won't take. Now the way תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* sort of frames this is basically I'm concerned that there
are other כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* that need it more than me. So
I won't take it because I understand that even to just receive,
although that's maybe showing my desire to do a nice מצוה *mitzvah*,
but if there's not enough to go around and other people need
it more than me, let me be the one to step back
and let somebody else take it. Okay, so then however לבר ממעלי
יומא דכיפורי *levar mi-malei yoma de-kippurai*, except for ערב יום כיפור Erev
Yom Kippur. *erev Yom Kippur*, why? לאחזוקי נפשאי בכהונה *Lachazukei nafshai bi-khahuna*,
that people should know that I'm a כהן Kohen *Kohen*. Now the
question is weren't there other ways like you get, you know, you
get an עליה Aliyah. *aliyah* whatever, דוכנין *duchening*, we'll talk about that
in a minute, but תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* points out... Why ערב יום
כיפור? Because he says there, everybody is eating meat ערב יום כיפור.
If you remember, we talked about that before. It was a time
that everybody ate meat and they slaughtered whatever and there by if
you're not taking the gift, you're people will say will assume the
only reason a person wouldn't take it is if they weren't a
כהן. Kohen Meaning other times it's like you're not making a statement
that you are, but you're not making a statement that you're not.
But when everybody, all the כהנים Kohanim are getting it and you're
the one person not getting it, then it seems to be making
a statement that you're not a כהן. Kohen So that's when I
felt that it was important for me to take. תוספות Tosafot says
ואילו לא היה נוטל היו אומרים שאינו כהן. ve'illu lo hayah notel
hayu omerim she'eino Kohen. Okay, so that's when I take. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says וליפרוס ידיה, velifros yadeih, why doesn't he do
ברכת כהנים? Birkat Kohanim? So the גמרא Gemara says אנסיה ליה עדנא,
anseiah leh idna,
his time was pressured him, which means what? So some say it
means that he was sick and he could not make he wasn't
healthy and he could never make it to שול. shul. רש"י Rashi
says it means that the time for the מנין minyan got in
was scheduled against the time when he had to sort of teach
the students or whatever. So therefore he never got to שול. shul.
So some of the challenges about being teaching a שיעור shiur like
a דף יומי Daf Yomi anyway in your congregation. Yeah, okay.
But the interesting thing is the גמרא Gemara doesn't ask about why
didn't he get an עליה. Aliyah? How about getting an עליה? Aliyah,
Maybe that was less frequent, maybe there were other also because yeah,
that's interesting, but as a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham it would have
been evident. Maybe it's not every single day, like you know they
only do עליות Aliyot like two three days a week. So maybe
that had understood he wasn't necessarily in שול shul when they read
תורה, Torah, but נשיאת כפיים nesiat kapayim was every day. It could
also be the point that תוספות made before, which is that it's
that the problem is is that when you're not getting it when
when you're not doing it and everybody else is. So an עליה,
Aliyah other people are around to get the עליה presumably. So the
fact that he's not getting it doesn't prove one thing or the
other. Okay, whereas he whereas he made a point that was the
time when everybody is doing something, then I make a point to
do it as well. So he says well that's נשיאת כפיים, nesiat
kapayim, all the כהנים kohanim have to do it. So isn't that
argue always making the statement then? Yes.
Then he's not a כהן.
Kohen
Well the answer is he never made it to שול, shul, that's
why he never had the opportunity to do it in that context.
Yes.
This this seems to be one more one more of many examples
where the תלמוד Talmud doesn't seem to put a great value on
תפילה בציבור. tefillah betzibbur.
Well, that's an interesting point. Certainly for the you know for the
for the rabbis and תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim, you know there's the
whole story about you know the קריאת שמע Kriat Shema of רבי
יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, like he said just the first פסוק
pasuk and it was like in the middle of his שיעור shiur
when somebody was asking a question he was going like this for
two seconds and say the first פסוק Pasuk. of שמע. Shema. So
certainly the pressure of, you know, teaching תורה Torah versus תפילה tefillah
and the whole that's a whole ongoing theme in ברכות, Berachot, you
know, that you know the one rabbi goes so far say when
people were davening a long שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei he says עוזבים
חיי עולם ועוסקים בחיי שעה, ozvim chayei olam ve'oskim bechayei sha'ah, they
leave eternal life which is the learning of תורה Torah and they
emphasize and they focus on their davening which is just asking for
temporal things. So certainly there's a whole tension there that is true.
And actually, you know, historians have said and it's clear from all
the evidence that the
authority and control of the בתי כנסיות batei kenessiyot were a different
sort of system of authority than the rabbinic authority. Meaning so there
was, you know, there's never an indication and it's pretty much if
you read the גמרא Gemara you sort of get this sense too
that the rabbis are not dictating what goes on in the שול.
shul. The שולס shuls are running totally independent of the rabbis. And
the rabbis were... yeah, there you go.
But no, it really was they were very much different like sort
of communities and authority structures and so on. No, no, no, no,
but it's not you weren't a rabbi of a שול shul is
the point. That whole the rabbis were their class and they were
sitting and learning and teaching תורה Torah and the שולס shuls were,
you know, were very ancient or whatever and run totally independently. So,
so yes, the rabbis were not big שול shul goers is the
sense you get and they certainly but you know they were very
into תפילה בציבור tefillah betzibbur but there was always that tension. All
right, so anyway now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Praying in the ישיבות yeshivot and not in the שול? shul?
Yeah, so that's sort of what I was indicating. There's a lot
of that praying where they learn and praying in the ישיבות yeshivot
and so on. So there is that whole question interesting thing about
those different realms. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Boy, we
are we are we have a lot we are getting it's so
fascinating that we're not getting anywhere. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says,
where are we? Okay, so anyway that was quite fascinating about again
the way in which you receive it and the balance between wanting
to participate in the מצוה, but because the מצוה is about you
getting something, you know, does it how to do it in a
way that's shows respect and that is not misinterpreted. Okay. פאמר רב
יוסף האי כהנא דאית ליה צורבא מרבנן בשיבבותיה ודחיקא ליה מילתא. Pa'amar
Rav Yosef hai kahana de'it leh tzurba merabbanan beshivvavuteih vedachika leh milta.
Now we have a flip of the previous case where we had
a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham advising a כהן Kohen how to get
some money. Now we have a כהן Kohen. who has a תלמיד
חכם Talmid Chacham in his community and דחיקא ליה מילתא dachika leh
milta and he has pressured, meaning he has economic hardship, the תלמיד
חכם. Talmid Chacham. ליזכי ליה, Lizki leh,
so there it's easier. A כהן Kohen if he receives
זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vekeivah just hand them over to the
תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. Okay, ליזכי ליה מתנתא, Lizkei leh matnasa,
let him be זוכה, zocheh, meaning transfer ownership of the gifts to
the תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. Now, of course, once he receives it,
it's no חידוש chiddush to give him your gifts if you don't
need them. ואף על גב דלא אתי לידיה, V'af al gav d'lo
asi l'yadei,
and here's the חידוש, chiddush, even before you've received the gifts, you
can transfer them to the תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. How can you
do it? You don't own it yet.
So the גמרא Gemara says במכירי כהונה ולויה. b'makirei kehuna u'leviya.
There's an institution which is discussed in גיטין, Gittin, which is called
מכירי כהונה ולויה, makirei kehuna u'leviya, which, I mean, I call it
an institution, you could say it's a case, but it actually sounds
like it was an institution, which is that there's a כהן Kohen
that everybody, it's well-known, and he's the one that everybody in the
town gives to, which is not so fair to everybody else, but
okay. Or maybe more specifically, and this is the way it sounds
a little bit in גיטין, Gittin, you're the כהן Kohen. that our
family gives to. Like your family and our family have a relationship
with, and our family has always given to your family, and that's
the relationship. That's why it sounds like in גיטין Gittin where this
is discussed more of an institution of this thing of מכירי כהונה.
makirei kehuna. So in that case, the גמרא, Gemara
the הלכה halacha is to some degree,
you know, whether it's דאורייתא, d'oraisa, דרבנן, d'rabbanan, how exactly you explain
it, but to some degree, even before the gifts are given, it's
like you've already been זוכה zocheh in them. It's so established that
we're going to give to you, it's from the very moment that
they're separated off, it's like you already own them. So if that's
the case, and this person is a מכירי כהונה, makirei kehuna, he's
one that people give to on a regular basis, he can transfer
that ownership to the other person. Now, even there the question is,
but let's say it's before they even שחט shachted the cow, you
know, and there gets into interesting questions about can you sell something,
a דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo ba l'olam. And what if
it's לא בא לעולם, lo ba l'olam, it's not around yet, but
you're going, but you know you're going to get it. And for
example, a good example that's discussed in the רמב"ם Rambam and it's
also very relevant nowadays in terms of the stock market is, can
I sell, something is readily available in the market, can I pre-sell
it to you? Okay, like I know that the, you know, at
Key Food they sell a sugar for a dollar a, you know,
a dollar a bag and they always, there always is sugar there.
Okay, and you, and I say to you, you know, and I,
can I go ahead and I sell you that sugar? Not, I'm
your שליח. shaliach. Give me two bucks and I'll sell you a
bag of sugar. Okay, I don't have the sugar in my house,
but don't worry, I'll deliver it to you within an hour for
two bucks. So you give me two bucks, I don't have a
bag of sugar, but I go to Key Food and I get
it. Okay, so can I sell it to you if I don't
have it if it's immediately available? So that's very much also a
case of options, right, and so on. So anyway, this is a
question about a דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, but
something that is readily available and I can turn around and purchase
it from somebody else. So, you know, that seems to also be
somewhat of the context here. Like they, the people regularly שחט, shacht,
they regularly give it to this כהן Kohen and so on, so
he can pre-sell it to the other person.
And then give it to whoever the other person is right away.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, רבא ורב ספרא Rava v'Rav Safra איקלעו iklu לבי
מר יוחנה בריה דרב חנא בר אדא. l'bei Mar Yohana brei d'Rav
Chana bar Adda. So רבא Rava and רב ספרא Rav Safra came
to
this
person's house, מר יוחנה, Mar Yohana, Mr. Yohana, the son of רב
חנא בר אדא. Rav Chana bar Adda. ואמרי לה לבי מר יוחנה
בריה דרב חנא בר ביזנא, V'amri lah l'bei Mar Yohana brei d'Rav
Chana bar Bizna, another, maybe it was the grandfather who was ביזנא.
Bizna. Anyway, עביד להו עגלא תילתא, avid lehu egla tilsa, and he
made for them a עגלא תילתא. egla tilsa. Now what does תילתא
tilsa mean? Actually, we just had in this week's פרשה, parsha, right,
עגלה משולשת. egla meshuleshes.
So what's עגלא תילתא? egla tilsa? So it occurs a couple times
in the גמרא Gemara as some type of a very prized dish.
There are a couple of interpretations. One means that it was a
third-grown calf, it was very young and tender. Some say it means
that it was a third, the third calf of the, I was
going to say litter, but anyway, the third calf that the cow
had, that the cow had birthed. Somehow that was seen as very
precious.
Some say three years old. First of all, it's not a calf
if it's three years old. Actually, I was checking Jastrow to see
the range of different interpretations he has, so it was quite funny.
He actually said, he actually said a third-grown calf, then he said,
other, parentheses, wrong interpretation, three-year-old calf. So other, wrong, anyway, so okay.
Anyway, okay,
he made them this special calf, עגלא תילתא. egla tilsa. אמר ליה
רבא לשמעיה, Amar leh Rava l'shamayei, so רבא Rava said to the
servant there who was serving them the meat, this מר יוחנה's Mar
Yohana servant, attendant, who happened to be a כהן. kohen And it
was known that the master of the house, מר יוחנה, Mar Yohana,
gave the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa, lechayayim, v'keiva to his servant, okay,
to his attendant. So רבא Rava knew this attendant now was going
to get the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa, lechayayim, v'keiva. So he said
to him, זכי לן מתנתא, zachi lan matnasa,
please transfer over to us your gifts, דבעינא למיכל לישנא בחרדלא, d'beina
l'meichal lishna b'chardala,
I'd like to eat the tongue in mustard. So they were getting
this fancy gift, so רבא Rava said, oh, would you mind giving
us your זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa, lechayayim, v'keiva that you're getting out
of this? I'd like to eat that tongue with mustard.
So זכי ליה, zachi leh, so he transferred it over to him.
So רבא אכל, Rava achal, רבא Rava ate this, ורב ספרא לא
אכל, v'Rav Safra lo achal, he refused to eat from this tongue.
אקריוהו לרב ספרא בחלמא, Akriuhu l'Rav Safra b'chelma, so in the, in
his dream, the following פסוק Pasuk was read to רב ספרא. Rav
Safra. What was it? מעדה בגד ביום קרה Maade beged beyom karah
a worn-out cloak on a cold day, חומץ על נתר Chometz al
neter or like vinegar on like some type of an of an
of a metal, ושר בשירים על לב רע Veshar beshirim al lev
ra like singing songs on to somebody with an evil with a
bad heart. So the somehow that was okay, whatever it was, it
wasn't good. But presumably שר בשירים Shar beshirim is like Torah and
bad heart, the implication was, you know, you know, you רב ספרא
Rav Safra were not, you know, did not accept the teaching. What
teaching didn't he accept? That a כהן kohen, can transfer over, you
know, ownership to a תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. So why is it
that you were refusing? That's at least the way he interpreted it.
All right, so that's we're getting there, but that's at least the
initial way it was interpreted.
But we should have known.
So אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף, Ata lekamei deRav Yosef, so now he
came to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר ליה, Amar leih, so רב
ספרא Rav Safra said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, דילמא משום דעברי
אשמעתא דמר, Dilma mishum deavri ashmata demar,
maybe because I went against your your teaching רב יוסף, Rav Yosef,
that you said that a כהן kohen can transfer ownership to a
תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. So אקריון הכי, Akriun hachi,
that's why they read me this פסוק. Pasuk So אמר ליה, Amar
leih, he said to him, no. כי אמרי אנא, Ki amri ana,
what was I talking about, what circumstances? באחר, Beacher,
if it's just a independent כהן. kohen, שמע, Shama, when you're talking
about the attendant, the servant, בעל כרחו מסר, Baal korcho masar, he
doesn't have a choice, right? You, the you know, you're an honored
guest, you say to the attendant, I'd like to have your זרוע
לחיים וקיבה, Zeroa lechayayim vekeiva, he he's not in a position to
say no. So you're essentially compelling him to do that. So that
one so I would never have suggested to do it in that
case. You did the right thing by not doing it. וכי אמרי
אנא, Vechi amri ana, not only that, when did I say? למאן
דלא אפשר ליה, Leman dela efshar leih, somebody a תלמיד חכם Talmid
Chacham who doesn't have the means, that that would be a nice
thing for a כהן kohen to transfer over. הא אפשר ליה, Ha
efshar leih, you have the means. So therefore of course you shouldn't
have done it there. You were totally right. ואלא מאי טעמא אקריון
הכי, Veela mai taama akriun hachi, so so why did they read
this פסוק Pasuk to רב ספרא Rav Safra if he didn't do
anything wrong? כלפי רבא, Klapi Rava, it was really referring to רבא.
Rava. רבא Rava was the one who did something wrong for exactly
this reason. He pressured the attendant, he had he had he was
a person of means, he shouldn't have done this to the poor
attendant. וליקריון לרבא, Velikriun leRava, so why not so why not read
this פסוק Pasuk? to רבא, Rava, why read it to רב ספרא?
Rav Safra? רבא נזוף הוה, Rava nazuf hava, because רבא Rava was
being was sort of like being נזוף, Nazuf, what's the appropriate like
not rejected but like sort of scorned.
רבא Rava was being scorned. They didn't want to have a conversation
with רבא. Rava. He did this bad thing, so they read the
פסוק Pasuk to רב ספרא, Rav Safra, which is a little funny.
So actually it reminded me of a Yiddish phrase, Joe, you might
know this, that Rabbi Katz at the Yeshiva said to me, I'd
forgotten it in Yiddish, I asked him to send it to me.
So I'm going to tell you what this Yiddish phrase is that
means this, because it was exactly appropriate to this. Do you know
what I'm talking about, Joe? Yeah, I'll read I gotta find it,
here it is, he emailed it to me. Tell me if you
know this Yiddish phrase. די טאכטער זאג איך די שנור מיין איך.
Der tochter zog ich, di shner mein ich. Do you know did
I say that right? Say say it correctly, what? You say something
else. Yeah,
I'm talking to my daughter, but I mean my daughter-in-law. I can't
say this to my daughter-in-law, so I'm going to tell my daughter,
right?
So it's like, you know, so they couldn't say it to רבא
Rava who they had to say it to, they don't want to
talk to רבא, Rava, so they said it to רב ספרא. Rav
Safra. What? In a dream, in a dream, right. Whoever the angels
are, whatever it was, that heaven you know didn't want to have
that conversation with רבא, Rava, you know they were too angry at
him, so they had it with רב ספרא. Rav Safra. All right.
All right, anyway, so all right,
so he was אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי, Amar leih Abaye leRav
Dimi, so אביי said to רב דימי, Rav Dimi, ופשטי דקרא במאי
כתיב, Upashtei dekra bemai ketiv, how
what's the פשט Pshat of the פסוק? Pasuk Because somehow we read
this פסוק Pasuk to referring to somebody who had a Torah teaching
that they misused, but we're assuming that the פסוק pasuk is talking
about somehow something different, that's only slightly different. So אמר ליה, Amar
leih, בשונה לתלמיד שאינו הגון, Beshone letalmid sheino hagun, not somebody like
רבא Rava who generally of course is, you know, you know, a
תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and so on and appropriate, but just in
this case maybe didn't absorb it correctly. But the פשט Pshat of
the פסוק pasuk is teaching a תלמיד Talmid that that is a
not good person, something somebody of bad character that if you teach
them they're going to misuse the Torah and use the Torah actually
to undermine the Torah, to attack the Torah. Okay, so and now
we're actually going to be very critical not just of the תלמיד,
Talmid, but of the people that will teach a תלמיד Talmid who
is of bad character.
דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב
כל השונה לתלמיד שאינו הגון נופל בגיהנום.
Deamar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav kol
hashone letalmid sheino hagun nofel beGehinnom.
If you teach a תלמיד Talmid that's improper you'll fall in גיהנום
Gehinnom because you are, you know, again, it's not just it's going
to waste, but actually it will come back to hurt you. שנאמר
כל חשך טמון לצפוניו תאכלהו אש לא נפח ירע שריד באהלו, Sheneemar
kol choshech tamun litzfunav tochlehu esh lo nupach yera sarid beohalo, all
darkness or complete darkness is is is hidden for the for these
hidden things, תאכלהו אש לא נפח Tochlehu esh lo nupach will eat
him fire that has not been sort of blown, meaning this very
intense fire, ירע שריד באהלו Yera sarid beohalo
it is evil for the שריד Sarid in the tent. So what
does this mean? ואין שריד אלא תלמיד חכם, Veein sarid ela talmid
chacham, a שריד, Sarid, a remnant is a תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham.
The תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that G-d calls.
So it could mean if the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is evil,
he should in the tent of תורה Torah these things will happen
to him. The מהרש״א Maharsha does not like the idea that we're
reading תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, we wouldn't call a תלמיד שאינו הגון
talmid she'eino hagun תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. We also wouldn't call him
a this פסוק pasuk about ובשרידים אשר ה׳ קורא. u'vaseridim asher Hashem
korei. So he says the שריד sarid is the תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham who's doing the teaching. That if you are the תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham and you're teaching, but ירע באהלו, yera b'ohalo, it's evil
in the tent, if the people you're teaching is an evil person,
then all these bad things will happen to you. אמר רב זירא
אמר רב, Amar Rav Zeira amar Rav, כל השונה לתלמיד שאינו הגון,
kol hashoneh l'talmid she'eino hagun, if you teach a תלמיד talmid that's
not good, כזורק אבן למרקוליס, k'zorek even l'markulis,
it's like throwing a stone to the מרקוליס markulis which was this
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And the metaphor is pretty clear and the
מהרש״א Maharsha spells this out. He says when a person throws a
stone at the מרקוליס, markulis, you might think you're doing something that's
bad, denigrating the מרקוליס, markulis, but it's actually a form of serving
it. So he says you think you're doing something good, but you're
actually doing doing something bad. So here you're teaching this person of
bad character, you think but I'm teaching him תורה, Torah, but the
reality you're doing something good but in the end you're adding to
the evil because you're giving them weapons and tools to come and
attack the תורה. Torah. Okay, so
there you go. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כצרור אבן במרגמה, k'tzror even b'margemah,
like somebody who binds a stone in a sling, כן נותן לכסיל
כבוד, kein nosein l'ksil kavod,
is like the giving to the fool honor. And some have the
גרסא, girsa, ואין כבוד אלא תורה, v'ein kavod ela Torah, and quote
a פסוק that honor means תורה. Torah. Here the next פסוק says,
וכתיב, u'chtiv, לא נאוה לכסיל תענוג, lo na'aveh l'ksil ta'anug,
it is not good for the כסיל ksil this type of pleasure
and benefit, it is not something that you that you give. So
of course you have to fit that in with the statement about
כל העוסק בתורה שלא לשמה, kol ha'osek baTorah shelo lishmah, you should
always learn שלא לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה. shelo lishmah shemitoch
shelo lishmah ba lishmah. Actually within those there are two contradictory statements.
One is always learn שלא לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה. shelo
lishmah shemitoch shelo lishmah ba lishmah. The other is anybody who learns
שלא לשמה נוח לו שלא נברא, noach lo shelo nivra, better that
he had not been created. So תוספות there distinguishes and basically says
one is a person who has essentially good character or redeemable traits
that the process of learning will obviously elevate them. And the other
is somebody that is coming with specific intent to do bad and
to do evil and has a bad character and is actually doing
it as a way of undermining, as a way of sort of
giving them ammunition to go ahead and find a way to be
destructive. And that's where these types of statements are. So it certainly
but there was always that tension about do you say like אלף
נכנסים ואחד יוצא, elef nichnasim v'echad yotzei, or nobody should come in
only a תלמיד שתוכו כברו, talmid shetocho k'voro, whose inside is like
his outside, only somebody of the highest character, or do you say
no you have a more sort of open policy because you hope
that the process is something that transforms people. So there's always those
gray areas but these are certainly talking minimally about the black areas,
areas where clearly there's very little hope that this will help the
person and in the end it actually is going to be something
that will be counterproductive.
Yes, in your ישיבה. yeshiva. There you go.
We only have the best students in our ישיבה. yeshiva. Okay,
moving on. המשתתף עמהן צריך לרשום. Hamishtatef imahen tzarich lirshom. Now back
to the משנה. mishnah. If you go into business with the כהן
kohen, or the non-Jew, then you have to although we said before
that in general that you can't do this as a policy of
getting out, but let's say you genuinely are in business with
a כהן, kohen then you're exempt, although even there we saw you're
only exempt for two or three weeks, but okay whatever it is
in this one cow this is half owned by a כהן kohen
and you're not going to give זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim v'keivah,
you make a mark on the cow so people understand why you're
not giving it to the כהן, Kohen why you're not giving it.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואפילו עם עובדי כוכבים, v'afilu im ovdei kochavim, do you really need
to make the mark even if your partner's with a non-Jew? ורמינהו,
U'reminhu, I'll ask you on this, המשתתף עם כהן צריך לרשום, hamishtatef
im kohen tzarich lirshom, with a כהן Kohen, you have to make
a mark, והמשתתף עם עובדי כוכבים ופסולי מוקדשים, v'hamishtatef im ovdei kochavim
u'psulei mukdashim, if you do it with a non-Jew or if the
animal was a redeemed sacrifice so you don't give gifts from redeemed
sacrifices, אין צריך לרשום, ein tzarich lirshom, you don't make a mark.
Now why is it different? Presumably in the last two cases it's
more obvious to people that those are the circumstances. So פסולי מוקדשים,
psulei mukdashim, something that was once a קרבן, korban, you could say
maybe people know, everybody is very sensitive to animals that were a
קרבן korban and so on, maybe it's more known. But how do
people know more that your partner's with a non-Jew partner's with a
כהן, Kohen why would there be a difference? So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinan, what are
we talking about? דיתיב עובד כוכבים אמסחתא, d'yasiv oved kochavim amaschata, the
non-Jew is sitting right there by the store watching you sell, so
supervising, so people understand he's your partner. גמרא Gemara says one minute,
דכוותיה גבי כהן דיתיב
אמסחתא, d'chvoseih gabei kohen d'yasiv amaschata, so but so what you talking
about parallel cases? So the parallel case would be the כהן Kohen?
is sitting there watching the business. So that also is obvious to
people. Why do you need to mark?
אמאי צריך לרשום, Amai tzarich lirshom,
why do you have to mark? So no, דאמרי, d'amri, like Michael
say, בישרא קזבין, bisra kazvin, no they see the כהן Kohen there
they think that he's buying meat. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי
הכי עובד כוכבים נמי אמרי בישרא קזבין, ei hachi oved kochavim nami
amri bisra kazvin, they'll also think the non-Jew is buying the meat.
This was before This was before כשר kosher meat was twice as
expensive as non-כשר kosher meat, or maybe they like, anyway, so people
will can equally assume that even if a non-Jew is at a
butcher, they can assume that
he is buying כשר kosher meat. So if, so either they'll all
assume that he's your partner, or they'll assume he is a, he's
a, you know, he's a customer. But why will they make different
assumptions by the כהן Kohen than by the non-Jew? So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, ela hacha bemai askinan, what do
we talking about? דיתיב עובד כוכבים אכספתא, deyativ oved kochavim akasfata,
he's counting the money. So after everything goes in, he's there with
the books, he's figuring out how much money you're taking in, or
the way רש״י Rashi says it is, he's actually, he's watching over
the money box. As the butcher takes the money, he puts it
in a money box, he's guarding the funds. So you know that
he's your business partner.
So גמרא Gemara says דכוותיה גבי כהן, dechvatai gabei Kohen, so the
same thing by a כהן, kohen דיתיב אכספתא. deyativ akasfata. So you'd
have to say the parallel case, so there too they'll know the
כהן kohen is your business partner. אמאי צריך לירשום, ammai tzarich lirishom,
why do you have to mark the animal by a כהן? kohen
So אמרי הימוני הימניה. amri heimunei heimneih.
No, by a כהן kohen people understand he might not be your
business partner, but you just trust him to watch your money. So
עובד כוכבים נמי אמרי הימוני הימניה? oved kochavim nami amri heimunei heimneih?
So why don't they say that you're trusting this non-Jew to watch
your money? So you know what's coming. So גמרא Gemara says אין
הימונא בעובד כוכבים. ein heimuna be'oved kochavim. You can't trust non-Jews. Now,
you read it this way, it's a very blanket statement. רש״י Rashi
takes the sting out of it a little bit. If you look
at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says by אין הימונא בעובד כוכבים, ein
heimuna be'oved kochavim, רש״י Rashi says,
where are we?
רש״י Rashi says
about twelve lines down, אין ישראל רגילים להאמין בהם. ein Yisrael regilim
leha'amin bahem.
Shifts it to an objective statement as to a social statement, if
you would, or a societal statement. Jews don't generally trust non-Jews. Whether
they can or can't be trusted isn't the point, it's not the
point, it's not the practice for Jews to trust non-Jews. Okay, which
is certainly makes the statement more palatable, you know, it's certainly just
descriptive rather than, anyway, evaluative. Anyway, so that's what he says. That
people wouldn't assume that you're trusting the non-Jew. That's not what he's
into.
What? You have to mark it because people don't generally trust them,
and you know what I mean.
All right, anyways, so גמרא Gemara says, so איבעית אימא, ibayis eima,
if you want we can go back to our other case, not
that he's watching over the money, that he's just there sitting in
the store. And nevertheless, סתם עובד כוכבים מפטפט. stam oved kochavim mefap-peit.
Here's, here the
גמרא Gemara is making at least an objective statement from its perspective,
which is the difference is like this. A, now,
it's funny about you talk about what is it called about reversing
stereotypes or whatever, I don't know. Anyway, so a normal non-Jew will
be, will be too much talking too much and supervising too much.
Meaning if the כהן kohen is sitting there, he'll be sitting there
quietly just observing, so people might think he's a customer. But if
your non-Jew partner is sitting there, he's going to say, "Oh, don't
sell him that piece, sell him that piece, oh you're not charging
enough," and he'll be, he'll be giving too much direction and it'll
be very obvious to everybody that he's your partner.
Talk about a stereotype.
That's what I just said, reversing the stereotype. Okay, anyway, all right,
so that's why somehow by a non-Jew it'll be more obvious and
you don't need to mark.
אמר מר, amar mar, what?
What's this? He talks too much, chatters too much, yeah. So אמר
מר, amar mar, ופסולי מוקדשין אין צריך לירשום, u'psulei mukdashin ein tzarich
lirishom, you don't have to do it by, by things that were
redeemed קרבנות. korbanot. אלמא מוכחא מילתא, alma mukcha milta, presumably it's known
that things used to be a קרבן. korban. והא אנן תנן, ve'ha
anan tenan, didn't we teach in a משנה? Mishnah? פסולי מוקדשין נמכרין
באיטליז ונשחטין באיטליז ונשקלין בליטרא. psulei mukdashin nimkarin be'itliz ve'nishchatin be'itliz ve'nishkalin
be'litra.
You can sell פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin in the marketplace and שחט
shacht them in the marketplace and weigh them out by the pounds.
Now, why, what does that mean? It means the following, that
when
you redeem a קרבן, korban, you redeem it for if it has
a blemish, you redeem it for how much its value is, how
much you can get for it. So although חז״ל Chazal were concerned
that when you sort of sell the meat of a קרבן korban
in the marketplace, and if you've ever been in like a שוק,
shuk, you know, you know it's like a whole בלאגן balagan or
whatever, you know, it might not be so respectful to something that
used to be a קרבן. korban. But nevertheless, it's worth that cost,
that, that
because you'll ultimately get a lot more money for it if you're
selling it in a marketplace and you know, and you're selling it
bit by bit than if you sell it private out of your
home. And therefore it means you'll redeem it for more money. So
they allowed by פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin to sell it in the
marketplace and to sell it by the pound because ultimately that means
it'll be of greater value.
Now, so what couldn't you do? You couldn't sell בליטרא. be'litra.
By, now by a בכור bechor or מעשר ma'aser, that has a
מום, mum, a מעשר, ma'aser. an animal that's a מעשר, maaser those
you don't redeem. You eat them with a מום mum but you're
not allowed to redeem. So since you don't redeem them, הקדש hekdesh
is not going to lose out, right? And therefore they didn't let
you sell that in the marketplace. Okay, you can sell it and
get the money, but it can't be redeemed. It's eaten as a
בכור bechor with a מום mum or whatever. So therefore הקדש hekdesh
is not getting the money there, so they didn't let you sell
that in the marketplace. So now, why is this relevant? It's relevant
because, so, אה, so it's not obvious. If you're selling it in
the marketplace like all the other meat, so how is it obvious
that this was פסולי המוקדשין? Psulei HaMukdashin. Okay, so the גמרא says
תרגמה רב אדא בר אהבה קמיה דרב פפא באוזן הן נמכרין בתוך
הבית. targema Rav Adda bar Ahava kammai de'Rav Pappa be'ozen hen nimkarin
betoch habayis.
Just like the, Michael said, there are some that you're not allowed
to sell in the marketplace, בכורים bechorim and מעשר. Those because it's
basically not respectful to sell it in the marketplace and those are,
those הקדש... hekdesh... without, because it's not redeemed, so those they demanded
that you sell it out of the house and you don't necessarily
sell it by the pound, you more sell it by the unit.
Now in those types of cases, if that's how you're selling your
meat, it's very obvious that it's פסולי המוקדשין. Psulei HaMukdashin So you're
right, normal פסולי המוקדשין it's not obvious, and therefore you would have
to make a mark, but the בכור bechor and the מעשר it
is obvious because of the way you're selling it and you don't
have to make a mark. Okay, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
so רב הונא Rav Huna says, שותף בראש shutfut berosh פטור מן
הלחי. patur min halechi. What type of partnership gets you out? So
basically
only if the כהן kohen is a partner in the part of
the animal that you would give the מתנות כהונה matnot kehunah from,
or the whole animal obviously. So if you're a partner in the
head, then you don't have to give the cheek area, the cheek
or the jaw. שותף ביד, shutfut beyad, if you're a partner in
the arm, פטור מן הזרוע, patur min hazroa, you don't have to
give the זרוע zroa which is like the lower arm. שותף בבני
מעיים, shutfut bivnei meayim, if he's a partner only in the in
the in the intestines, פטור מן הקיבה, patur min hakeivah, you don't
give the stomach. So and obviously if you're a partner in the
whole בהמה behemah you don't give any. But the point is if
you're only let's say I've only bought the hind quarters of the
בהמה, behemah, then it would and I'm a כהן kohen it would
not get you out of giving the gifts. I have to have
a part ownership in these gifts themselves. So, וחייא בר רב אמר,
veChiya bar Rav amar, אפילו שותף באחת מהן פטור מכולן, afilu shutfut
be'achat mehen patur mikulan,
even if you're only partner in one of the gifts, they're all
a unit. So as long as the כהן kohen has an ownership
of part of one of the gifts, you're exempt from any of
them. So מתיבי, meitivei, a question on this. הראש שלי וכולה שלך,
harosh sheli vechulah shelcha, so let's say the כהן kohen says, I'll
keep the head, you get the rest of the animal, ואפילו אחד
ממאה בראש, ve'afilu echad mimeah berosh,
and even if the כהן kohen just retains ownership of one percent
of the head, פטור, patur, you're exempt. Now the question is exempt
from what? היד שלי וכולה שלך, hayad sheli vechulah shelcha, let's say
he says I'll keep the hand, you the ישראל Yisrael. keep the
rest of the animal, or אפילו אחד ממאה ביד, afilu echad mimeah
beyad, even if he only owns one percent of the hand, פטור,
patur, you're exempt. בני מעיים שלי וכולה שלך, bnei meayim sheli vechulah
shelcha, I'll keep the intestines, you get the rest, or אפילו אחד
ממאה בהן, afilu echad mimeah bahen, even if I have only he
only gets one percent of the intestines, פטור, patur, he's exempt. So
the fact that it divided it these ways, מאי לאו פטור מן
הלחי וחייב בכולן, mai lav patur min halechi vechayav bekulan, does it
not mean you're exempt from that, from that part of the animal?
So in the first case you're exempt from the the cheek and
the maw area, פטור מן הזרוע וחייב בכולן, patur min hazroa vechayav
bekulan, in the second case you're exempt from the arm but you're
חייב chayav in the rest, in the last case פטור מן הקיבה
וחייב בכולן, patur min hakeivah vechayav bekulan, you're exempt from the stomach.
So since it divided into three cases, presumably when it says you're
exempt, it means you're exempt from that local gift but not all
the gifts. So גמרא says לא, no, פטור מכולן, patur mikulan, it
means you're exempt from all of them. Once you're exempt, you're you
get off from all of them. וליתני פטור מכולן, velitni patur mikulan,
so say it explicitly since clearly that's not the implication. ועוד, ve'od,
and besides which, we have a ברייתא braita, that's explicit. תניא, tanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, braita הראש שלי וכולה שלך, harosh sheli
vechulah shelcha, I keep the head you keep the rest, אפילו אחד
ממאה בראש, afilu echad mimeah berosh, even one percent of the head,
פטור מן הלחי, patur min halechi,
you're exempt from the maw area, וחייב בכולן, vechayav bekulan, but you
have to give the other two gifts. תיובתא דחייא בר רב תיובתא,
tiyuvta deChiya bar Rav tiyuvta, that is a complete contradiction. So the
ruling is you only the ownership of the כהן kohen gets you
off the hook only for the gifts for which he has a
portion of. So if he has one percent of the of the
intestines, you're off from the stomach, you're חייב chayav for the rest.
If he has one percent of the whole בהמה, behemah, you're off
for everything because he has a percentage, a piece of all of
the gifts. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says, הא מתניתין אתיסיה לחייא בר רב, ha matnitin atisya leChiya
bar Rav, the following ברייתא braita was what made חייא בר רב
Chiya bar Rav err to think that they were all one unit.
Why did the following ברייתא braita, make him think that all three
gifts were treated as one unit? דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא,
עשרים וארבע מתנות כהונה הן, esrim ve'arba matnot kehunah hen, there are
twenty-four gifts of the כהן in all total, וכולן ניתנו לאהרן ולבניו
בכלל ופרט, vekulan nitnu le'Aharon ulevanav bichlal uferat,
they were all given specifically, the תורה Torah specifies generally, here are
the gifts, you know, these will be for you the gifts, as
a general statement, and a specific statement, it lists them, וברית מלח,
uvrit melach, and says at the end particularly this is in קרח,
Korach, it says these are given to you with a covenant of
salt, a permanent covenant that they are yours. כל המקיימן, kol hamekayman,
if you fulfill them, כאילו קיים בכלל ופרט וברית מלח, ke'ilu kiyem
bichlal uferat uvrit melach, it's like you fulfilled them in the general
and the specific and the ברית מלח. brit melach. וכל העובר עליהן,
vechol ha'over aleihen, if you transgress them, כאילו עבר עליהן בכלל ופרט
וברית מלח, ke'ilu avar aleihen bichlal uferat uvrit melach, like you fully
transgressed. Now reading it this way it means if you fulfill them
it's like you did them all the perfect way and if you
transgress it's like you fully transgressed. But רש"י Rashi says if you
fulfill them it's like you fulfilled all of the כללים klalim and
פרטים pratim in the תורה, Torah, meaning it's like you filled everything
בכלל ופרט, bichlal uferat, you know, using it as a larger metaphor
for the whole תורה. Torah. Anyway, ואלו הן, ve'elu hen, these are
the gifts. עשר במקדש, eser bamikdash, ten in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash. וארבע בירושלים, ve'arba biYerushalayim, four in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ועשר בגבולין, ve'eser
bigvulin, and ten in the rest of ישראל. Yisrael עשר במקדש, eser
bamikdash, here are the ten things the כהן gets in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, חטאת, chatat, he gets to eat the meat of
the חטאת, chatat, חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, a bird חטאת, chatat, אשם,
asham, the אשם asham which is similar to a חטאת, chatat, ואשם
ודאי ואשם תלוי, ve'asham vadai ve'asham taluy, so the אשם asham brought
for a definite sin and the אשם asham brought for a doubtful
sin, וזבחי שלמי ציבור, vezivchei shalmei tzibur, the communal שלמים shlamim which
is really only on שבועות, Shavuot, you brought lambs as a communal
שלמים, shlamim, the כהנים kohanim eat the meat, ולוג שמן של מצורע,
velog shemen shel metzora, the log of oil of a מצורע, metzora,
part of his purification process, what's left over the כהן and eat,
ושתי הלחם, v'shtei halechem, the two loaves of bread of שבועות, Shavuot,
I hope people are keeping count, ולחם הפנים, v'lechem hapanim, the bread
on the שולחן, shulchan, the twelve loaves of bread, ושאר המנחות, v'shear
haminchot, what's left over from a מנחה mincha they eat in the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash ומנחת העומר, v'minchat haomer, the מנחת העומר minchat
haomer which is the one case of a communal מנחה mincha that
they eat, so that's why it's listed separately. Those are the ten
gifts that are given in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. and that
they eat them in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. They can't go
out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash וארבע בירושלים, v'arba b'Yerushalayim, Michael
please, you can...
we'll talk about it later. And four in ירושלים: Yerushalayim: הבכורה, habechorah,
the firstborn of the animals, והביכורים, v'habikkurim,
the first fruit, and these are given in the בית... Beis... well,
the ביכורים bikkurim are given in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but
they're eaten in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ומורם מתודה ומאיל נזיר, umuram
mitodah ume'eil nazir,
the gift from the תודה todah and not only תודה, todah, שלמים
shlamim and the ram of a נזיר. nazir. There, the ram of
a נזיר nazir you give the זרוע, zero'a, the arm, but by
the תודה todah you give the חזה chazeh and the שוק, shok,
the breast and the thigh, and you even give some loaves of
bread. All of those things are קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, so you
give them in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, but they're eaten in
all of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ועורות קדשים, v'orot kodshim, and the skin of sacrifices. They
got the skin even of an עולה, olah, they got the leather,
okay, but that they could use in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Not
outside? Presumably not. ועשר בגבולין, v'eser bigvulin, ten in all of Israel:
תרומה, terumah, ותרומת מעשר, v'terumat ma'aser, תרומה terumah that a ישראל gives,
תרומת מעשר terumat ma'aser that a לוי gives, חלה, challah, right, when
you make dough, ראשית הגז, reishis hagez, the shearings, מתנות, זרוע לחיים
וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim v'keivah,
here's the point that it's mentioned as one, not as three, ופדיון
הבן, u'pidyon haben, redeeming the firstborn, ופדיון פטר חמור, u'pidyon peter chamor,
the first of a donkey, ושדה אחוזה ושדה חרמים, v'sdei achuzah v'sdei
charamim,
certain fields when they're dedicated to the בית המקדש, they go to
the כהנים kohanim. at the יובל yovel or at other times, וגזל
הגר, v'gezel hager,
and if you steal from a גר, ger, a convert, and you
swear and deny it, and then when you admit and if the
person is dead, who do you give it to? You give it
to the כהנים. So those are they. Now, the מתנות are listed
only as one.
מאן סבר, man savar,
he assumed, מדקחשיב להו למתנות בחדא, midkachashiv lehu lematanot bechada,
since it counts them as only one unit, חדא נינהו, chada ninhu,
they're all one unit and if you're exempt from one, you're exempt
from all. לאו היא, lav hi, it's not true. אטו מורם מתודה
ואיל נזיר דקחשיב להו כחדא, atu muram mitodah v'eil nazir dekachashiv lehu
kechada,
you know what else it counts as one? The gift you give
from a כהן from a תודה todah and from the ram of
a נזיר. nazir. Those are very different. One is a חזה chazeh
and שוק, shok, the other is a זרוע. zero'a. משום דחדא נינהו?
mishum dechada ninhu? Are they really one? אלא כיון דדמיין להדדי, ela
kivan dedamyan lehadadi, since they're similar, they're קדשים קלים kodshim kalim that
the כהן gets a part of it, חשיב
להו כחדא, chashiv lehu kechada, it counted as one. הכא נמי, hacha
nami, here too, כיון דדמיין להדדי, kivan dedamyan lehadadi, they're similar, חשיב
להו כחדא, chashiv lehu kechada, they're one, but they do not... they're
not halachically treated as one unit, but for the purpose of counting,
also there's a nice symmetry, ten, four, and ten, it's an easy
way to remember it, so we want to manipulate the numbers a
little bit to get it to be that way, so therefore we
count it as one, but it does not mean halachically they're only
treated as one unit.